[Music]
yesterday we discussed the index of a
vector
field we are looking at a vector field
the kind that you learn in Vector
calculus analysis of vector
Fields but we trying to apply
topological methods to such studies and
we'll understand lots of things about
dynamical systems and we try to do
Vector Fields study Vector Fields not
only on R2 R3 as we do in elementary
courses on Vector calculus but also on
any manifold any surface any manifold so
index of vector field um at an
equilibrium
and
we yesterday was just introd
introduction to various Concepts but
today we'll start this Theory which will
lead us to some interesting results the
first one
is a theorem that is comparable to
another theorem that we saw in the last
chapter this theum five from last
chapter says that when you look at the
problem of finding fixed
points the inter intersection number of
a graph together with its um diagonal
rather diagonal and the graph is
invariant when you deform the mapping so
that you can um change the mapping in a
continuous fashion and still have the
same number of fixed points counted with
positive and negative signs here it's a
similar
theorem in order to apply the
intersection Theory you have to always
assume that
the underly objects are closed in there
are no boundaries you remember what
happens to intersection numbers when you
have a boundary if you have a boundary
the intersection number can change in
the course of the deformation because an
intersection Point can fall off the
boundary or appear from the boundary but
if you have a closed station there's no
such danger so if m is closed
then the sum of the all the index
indices of Vector field i x where
X sums over all the
equilibrium of v v is the vector field
and x x is a point of the manifold is
invariant so um is
invariant and the deformations any
deformations continuous deformations of
the vector field
okay and what do we mean and
deformations but V really we mean
under isotopies of the
graph of the graph of B inside the space
that you already know inside the tangent
that's what really me but you can think
intuitively about having a vector field
you see at each point you have a vector
touched in a continuous fashion and then
you start modifying that or even more
pictorially think of the flow of some
fluid for example water flowing and
there's a very intricate pattern there
might be a sort of swirling Vortex here
and there might be a rapid part here and
then there might be another water coming
and so forth and that pattern of the
flow starts changing when it changes
some of the um equilibria might
disappear some of the equili some
equilibrium might appear but the number
that we have written down the sum of all
the indices Remains the Same okay and
that's quite obvious because we saw that
the intersection
number is always the same and this sum
of indices um we proved um we are going
to prove in fact is
um um is invariant under the deformation
of these things okay so this is in fact
obvious from the main theorem of the
intersection
Theory which was theorem
17 two chapters this theorem 17 when we
encountered it I said was the chief
theorem of the um of the entire course
and in fact we keep using it as you
see a little mo is true so it turns
out not only is this number
invariant you see because this number is
invariant in order to calculate how many
equilibria you have for a given Vector
field you can start to modifying the
vector field to something easier and
then calculate do you remember the
spirit of this entire course and also of
the topological approach to
mathematics suppose you have a problem
the problem might look difficult then
what you do try to do is to deform the
problem to something easier and then if
you manage to find an easier problem to
which you can deform the original
problem solve the easier problem and
then take the solution and deform it
back to the original problem and thus
you can find a difficult Solution by
solving an easier problem here is the
same thing you might want to deform V
but often what really gets in the way is
well can you deform the and problem to
something easier that part requires
inspiration however in the case of
vector Fields dist is amazingly nice it
turns out that any two Vector Fields can
be deformed to each other here's
statement any two Vector fields on the
same
manold Vector Fields let's denote them
by V and W so these are two vectors
fields on the same
man on
M can be deformed to each
other continuously
in in other words the graphs are
isotopic to each other for any two
Vector fields which is
quite nice um maybe I shall write it in
the language of the intersection Theory
as well the
it means that the graphs are
isotopic Y and inside this isotop is
inside tangent of course
okay proof and you can do it by
pictures or do you can do it by
formula our cartoon picture of the
tangent bundle looks like this as you
remember this is the tangent bundle and
at each point we are
considering the tangent
space
okay you might
have the vector field which is
represented like that you remember what
this means it means that at each point I
have some value of this Vector field
which means that I have a vector
attached to this point Vector which is
tangent to this manifold also you might
have gamma of w which might look like
this okay so I want to deform this
yellow thing to the red thing well how
do I do that well there's an easy way to
do it at each point you see this line
that we are seeing is in fact a vector
space okay it's a tangent space to
tangent Vector space to M at this point
and we have one point and one point in
the tangent space two points so I can go
from I think
you see here the vector is like this
maybe and Vector is like this at each
point all you have to do in order to mod
deform them continuously is to connect
them and then start
deforming like that that's actually very
very easy right amazingly easy so what
we do is to deform between them like
that just inside each tangent
space rest you
only
once yeah so in formulas it's even
easier but perhaps this is easier to see
let's write it like 1 - s * gamma of V +
S * gamma of w where s runs between 0
and 1 so s is the deformation parameter
and you see what happens when s is zero
you get gamma V plus Z but as s
increases you get less and less of gamma
V and more and more of gamma W and at
the end when s is one you get just gamma
W this deformation is exactly
that and obviously this is a continuous
deformation I mean everything is
continuous right oneus s gamma and so on
so you can do this deformation
continuously which shows that any two
Vector Fields can be deformed to each
other in a continuous manner or they
isotopic each other within the tangent
bundle
well the two theorems 10 and 11 if you
think about them
logically these theorems imply the
following
conclusion the cor which is really the
useful one is that if m is
closed the sum of the indices of any
Vector
field again X is running over all the
equilibria of the given Vector
field does
not depend on the choice of this V
but is simply determined
by the manifold
itself is that
clear that's because
if one of you um Dina gives me a vector
field and and another one of you for
example ciso gives me another Vector
field let's call them V and W I claim
that the index of V at all its
equilibria and index of w at all its
equilibria those equilibria equilibrium
points will be different of course but
if you add up the indices you get
exactly the same number why is this
because I can take V from Dina and W
from teriso and I can deform them into
each other by this method the
yeah on the other hand by theem 10 in
the course of deformation I don't change
this number so in the beginning at the
end I get the same number so either way
whatever Vector field I I choose I
always at the end get the same number so
which shows that in fact this number
very interestingly doesn't have anything
to do with the vector field although
it's calculated in terms of the vector
field you see you you you imagine that
you're doing something very complicated
you take a vector field you look at all
its equilibria all the places where the
vector field becomes zero and then at
each point I have to calculate the index
you know by the method that we discussed
yesterday by the formula calculating the
yakobian and determinant and its sign
and so on and then you get plus minus
signs all over the place you add them
together and that's how you calculate
this number you think but because the
result actually does not depend on the
choice of the vector field this number
which you calculate by such a
complicated mechanism is a number which
M knows from the beginning
anyway you don't have to have the
information about the vector field in
order to calculate this
number and that remark um is
encapsulated in the um following
discussion so well
then can we
express this uh
number excuse
me this
thing
directly in terms
of
M information about
M Maybe
bless you
again and the answer is that you
can first a definition which will seem
familiar to
you we are about to introduce officially
in the lecture the oila characteristic
which you have already discussed in the
exercise session suppose that you have a
manifold you can imagine a surface if
you like and we shall say that we have
subdivided or partitioned this manifold
into a
network
okay looks
familiar like this I don't know how you
would like to go this
like
that and so on and so on yeah you have
some such
Network
so given the
manifold let's say that its Dimension is
small M so that we have a letter to
refer to going manifold small M and
partition
[Applause]
it into what you might call a network
I'm not defining exactly what I mean by
network but I hope you'll understand as
well as I do network
of various objects first beta 0o
vertices beta one
edges and beta 2
faces and so on so on in this case we
shall keep going to high and high
dimensions for example if you have
vertices edges and faces in
threedimensional space you might have
those chambers or blocks that you count
the number would be beta 3 and so on so
I keep going
[Music]
and continue
here which is denot by Beta K the number
of K
dimensional blocks or
faces that you have in the count okay
and in
fact the official term is cells
interesting so One Zero Dimensional cell
is a vertex Zero Dimensional cell is a
vertex one dimensional cell is an
edge what is a face it's a
two-dimensional cell and so on okay
cells of various dimensions and there
are all cells in all Dimensions between
zero and up to m m is the top dimension
of the manifold okay we and please uh
note something that
we noted in the exercise session we have
to require something about those cells
these cells can be pretty much any shape
in the picture you see that it can be a
triangle
it can be a quadrilateral it can be
effectively a pentagon and so on but
they all have to look in some sense nice
and what nice means is that we
require
each K dimensional
cell to be
homeomorphic to the K dimensional
B the cell should not topologically look
like anything else we shall come back to
that remark in a
moment with this
preparation the key concept which
unfortunately I'm reing in this corner
of the black for more that I hope that
people in the back can see the oiler
characteristic of M is defined
in the way that you discovered most of
you discovered yourselves it's denoted
by the Greek letter he of M and it is
equal to the sum of plus or minus those
betas where you get the plus sign for
even dimensions and minus signs for odd
Dimensions this is what the oil
characteristic
is a very important concept
indeed and you see this concept in many
other areas of mathematics it's all over
mathematics for example in graph Theory
where you are talking about only
onedimensional manifolds essentially
graphs you get only beta0 and beta 1 so
you get beta 0 minus beta 1 that's the
other characteristic but there are
higher dimensional um analoges of graphs
in the manifolds and you calculate this
number let's check whether you have been
listening
huh for example um somebody
whose language is not maybe English
Fredo what is the name of this
letter what's his huh K Kai okay that's
very
interesting you call it Kai and do you
know how it's usually spelled it's
spelled
like
this in Greek that's a Greek letter it's
pronounced it's sound is he yeah for
example you know the word choreography
that's about
dancing or chronology and S you often
see CH in many spellings and it's that
letter in fact so chronology is in fact
Chronos in Greek time and choreography
is hor which is the dance and so on
so in Greek it's h but the many European
languages don't have H so they just
translit it as CH now the English
speakers think that when they see I it's
I not e so in French you can call it ke
or she or you can do that but English
speaker say hi and that's why you call
it Kai but you can call it key if you
like similarly many people say this
isai or Z even but really what it is
is so you don't have to be influenced by
you know English speakers you can call
it he that's the proper word any proper
name
okay
now we mentioned this number and we said
that he of M looks like the number
associated with M that there's no extra
information
required to write down what p is but you
see apparently it depends on all those
betas all those betas depend on how we
drew the picture if somebody else comes
along and draws a completely different
network all those betas will change and
maybe this number will change it turns
out luckily for us that this number is
invariant so we we shall prove later
on in
the theorem 15 so very soon
that this oila characteristic does not
depend on the choice of the on how we
partition partition
M I'm sure you're beginning to
appreciate the pattern here in
mathematics often we introduce some
quantity and that quantity for example
the index total index of a vector field
for example the intersection number
between two sub manifolds for example
the O characteristic and so on are
defined in terms of many choices we have
to make choices but then there is a
theorem that says all those choices in
fact didn't matter those numbers are
invariant so why do we bother making
choices isn't there a direct way of
defining them so that you don't have to
make any choices yes indeed there is a
direct method but that direct method
first of all can be very abstract and
complicated and secondly such a formula
can be used in two different
ways you can read it in two different
ways and we shall come to that in the
next theorem
but in the
meantime before the theorem let's look
at some examples as usual in order to
understand this
better we shall now compute or write
down all the all the characteristics of
all the
Spheres first what is the order
characteristic here of the Zero
Dimensional sphere well we should draw
the picture of the Zero Dimensional
sphere what what's
that just two points Min - one and + one
those are exactly the points on R1 that
are at distance one from the origin two
points so what is the count how many
vertices are there in this picture two
two how many edges please don't say
one there's no no Edge we're looking at
only those two points zero yeah so it's
zero so in fact those little lines are
not there I have only two points so beta
0 is two and there's nothing else so
that's the order characteristic okay
only vertices in this case Zero
Dimensional Zero Dimensional means
points only points how about one
dimensional
um sphere which is also known as a
circle well here is one way
to partition the circle yeah I drew this
and then I regard each of these as an
edge that's a perf partition okay so
what is this what's beta 0 and what's
beta
1 that's three and beta 1 is also three
so I have to put the minus sign there
it's plus- plus minus and that comes out
be zero interesting the oil
characteristic of this circle S1 is zero
what about S2 well there are different
ways of partitioning it but I'd like to
visualize S2 as let's say a
tetrahedron maybe I should do it as a
cube also but we can do that separately
so do you see my
picture and it looks funny but the
surface is homeomorphic to that of a
sphere two Dimension sphere I mean only
this surface yes um not the inside
okay it's a two- dimensional object so
we expect to have beta 0 beta 1 and beta
2 how many how many vertices are there
in the picture four four thank you who
said three 1 2 3 three No 1 2 3 4 now
how how about beta one how many edges
thank you
so 1 2 3 3 3 3 that's six okay and then
two beta 2 how many faces are there 1 2
3 4 and so minus plus and that comes out
to be help what's this huh two
that's again two curiously it's the same
two as this two so we keep going note
that let's Parry
here if we did the partitioning of the
sphere in a different way and I assume
that many of us would not have done the
partitioning of the sphere this way do
we get a similar answer in fact the same
answer let's think of the sphere as the
surface of a
cube okay again I'm talking only about
surface it's not one of those cubic
cheeses it's not a cubic cheese it's
just a shell it's a cheese whose inside
has been already eaten there's surface
there so what is this well beta 0 beta 1
beta 2 in this case how many vertices
are there eight eight and edges well at
the top there are four at the bottom
there are four but there are four
vertical ones so together 12 and how
many faces six faces because you know
when you have a die that you roll 1 2 3
4 5 six so minus plus note that beta has
changed beta0 has changed beta 1 has
changed beta 2 has changed everything
has changed but the when you do the
sum Al sum it's still
is the
same so indeed this example shows that
the characteristic key does not seem to
depend on the choice of the partition
and then we of course would like to find
out what would you like to find out
Trevor is an ambitious man after we do
this what would do that yeah S3 but in
general you're even more ambitious I
know so you want to find it for all
Dimensions what on Earth is this and you
can in fact Sol this
problem you can set up a recurrence we
can
represent
SM in the following
manner I'm going to draw a fairly large
picture so please draw a large picture
too by the way
um I have been observing my colleagues
for many many years mathematicians and
physicist and so on and I made a
discovery um I think that the quality of
math
I is proportional to the size of the
pictures that he or she
draws the bigger pictures a
mathematician draws the better
mathematician that person is so you know
many people when they are drawing a
picture draw something like this a
circle which is like
this another
Circle but if you're a good
mathematician which you all are you draw
a circle like this and then
so please draw not only many pictures
but lots of large
pictures okay so my cartoon picture is
as follows we have the Northern
Hemisphere I don't see why Northern
Hemisphere should be up and southern
hemisphere should be down we should
probably start drawing the picture the
other way one day and southern
hemisphere
this okay
and you have the
equator please note that if this is SM M
dimensional sphere the equator is s
minus one does that make sense let me
convince you that that's the case for
example when m is
two S2 this sphere the equator of S2 is
S1 the
circle indeed
if you have S1 a circle what's the
equator equator is simply those two
points and that's s0 and so forth so the
equator of SM is SM minus one sphere of
Dimension low one dimension
lower on the other hand those two
hemispheres
uh two cells in other words these are
each M dimensional
balls of Dimension m
example if you're talking about S2 if
this whole picture is S2 I'm claiming
that these are two dimensional cells but
what is a two dimensional cell it's B2
in other words a two- dimensional ball
in other words a dis so I'm saying that
if you take a
dis and another dis two discs and curve
the discs like this and like this and
glue them along the common boundary
which is the equ you get a sphere is
that
clear huh okay so Northern Hemisphere
southern hemisphere each of these is
homomorphic to a dis and so you can
regard them as two dimensional cells in
the in general M dimensional cells okay
so that's the representation so let's do
the
count if you look at
the count of the order characteristic
what we get is the
following first first we have the oil
characteristic coming from this equator
I don't know how many vertices and edges
and faces and so forth you get I'm
drawing a two dimensional picture but in
general this picture is valid for
Dimension M so let's do the count for
the oil characteristic here okay so you
get beta 0 beta 1 beta 2 all of these
coming from here so you get discount
first and
then you see here as long as we in the
equator S nus one we go up to Beta of
nus one because that's a top Dimension
but we can then construct this SM by
gluing two last cells those cells are M
dimensional cells right so
plus you have two
that's beta
n where the fact
min-1 to the m power so that's the
recurrence if you go from lower
Dimension to higher Dimension you can
each time go to the next order
characteristic by adding an extra term
like this okay so what does this become
then let's try to detect a pattern this
is M this is the oil characteristic of s
of M we have already seen some lower
dimensional
cases zero you get two
one you get zero two you get two so far
we know these data points let's see what
three is going to be so Kai of he of S3
is going to be he of S2 and then what
you
get huh what's this
ter huh
again what's this
time- minus two because m is three so 2
- 2 it is
zero by the way let's check that this is
working too so from one to two he of S2
two dimensional sphere should be he of
S1 which is zero plus - one to^ M * 2
what's m in this
case two so then what do you get here
two it's two so 0 + 2 is two so it's
working and you can check that this is
going to be 02 02 always alternating
okay it's easy to check and the
conclusion then
um which will satisfy Trevor is that
when you have an even dimensional
sphere the O characteristics to and an
OD Dimension
sphere the or characteristic is zero
okay A
little
um quiz for
you let's consider
R2 yeah it's the
plane and then I draw a sphere that is a
circle huh so we saw that this circle
has
o characteristic 3 - 3 is zero but look
it's in two dimensional
plane how come the order characteristic
is not
two huh so who else let's ask people in
the back do you have any justing you
know it's in
R2 and this thing three vertices and
three edges is 3 - 3 is zero so the O
characteristic of this circle is zero
although we are in two dimensional space
so shouldn't this be Order character
character be
two what's going
on are you mystified are you
puzzled this is a very common mistake
among beginners
what's going on is that we are inside R2
but the sphere itself is onedimensional
we have a one dimensional sphere in two
dimensional
space is that okay M dimensional sphere
is a subset of M plus one dimensional
space is that okay for example if you
have three dimensional space you look at
the set of all the points that are
distance one from the origin you get a
Surface a two dimensional object object
inside a threedimensional
space okay so this
Dimension s of M this m is the dimension
of the sphere itself not of the ambient
ukian space SM is inside R to n +1 but
that's not what we're talking about we
are talking about the dimensional sphere
so in that case we have a circle it's
S1 one dimensional spere that is a
circle inside R2 so we in this case or
the order characteristic is zero clear
good